Guide to the Nantucket Collection
Yale University. Department of Manuscripts and Archives
Nantucket collection
1663-1822
MS 1003
Yale University. Department of Manuscripts and Archives
0.25
Financial records, a diary, and legal documents relating to the Gardner, Pinkham, Swain, and Coffin families of Nantucket. Most prominent in the collection is Silas Gardner, with a diary, bills, and receipts (1776-1822). He was co-owner with his nephew, Paul Pinkham, Jr., of the schooner, Pomona, for which there are legal and financial papers. In addition there are papers relating to Grafton Gardner and George Swain, records for the sloop, Caroline (1798-1799), and documents concerning the division of the common lands of Nantucket (1663-1806).
Immediate Source of Acquisition
Purchased in 1953.
Conditions Governing Access
The materials are open for research.
Scope and Contents
This collection contains approximately 250 items which relate chiefly to Nantucket, Massachusetts, and to the Gardner, Pinkham, Swain, and Coffin families who lived there. The bulk of the collection consists of receipts, bills, accounts, and other financial papers, deeds, papers pertaining to estates and to several ships. There is also a small amount of correspondence, and a short diary kept by Silas Gardner (1753-1826). Silas Gardner is the person best represented in the collection; his nephew Paul Pinkham, Jr. (1763-1807) is also prominent in the collection. The latter was a trader living in Nantucket, Londonderry (New Hampshire), and Cape Porpoise (Maine), and co-owner with Peter Gardner of the sloop Pomona.
These papers were purchased for Yale University in 1953.
Shipping -- Massachusetts -- Nantucket Island; Massachusetts; Nantucket Island (Mass.) -- History; New England; Deeds; Diaries; Gardner, Grafton, 1707-1789; Gardner, Silas, 1753-1826; Pinkham, Paul, 1763-1807; Swain, George, b. 1762; Coffin family; Gardner family; Pinkham family; Swain family; Caroline (Sloop); Pomona (Schooner)
- Inventory
  - Correspondence, 1795-1817 (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - Gardner, Grafton (1707-1796): legal and financial papers, 1760-1796 (Box 1, Folder 2)
  - Gardner, Silas (1753-1826)
    - Bills and receipts by him, 1776-1814 (Box 1, Folder 3)
    - Bills and receipts to him, 1789-1822 (Box 1, Folder 4)
    - Diary, 1807-1809 (Box 1, Folder 5)
  - Pinkham, Paul, Jr. (1763-1807)
    - Bills and receipts to him, 1791-1807 (Box 1, Folder 6)
    - Financial papers by him, 1795-1799 (Box 1, Folder 7)
  - Swain, George: "Directions to and from the Point Light on the NE Point of Nantucket", undated (Box 1, Folder 8)
  - Nantucket, Mass., Proprietors of the Common Lands: papers relating to the division of common lands, 1663-1806 (Box 1, Folder 9)
  - Caroline (sloop): bills and receipts, 1798-1799 (Box 1, Folder 10)
  - Pomona (schooner): legal and financial papers, 1798-1799 (Box 1, Folder 11)
  - Miscellaneous papers, 1793-1797 (Box 1, Folder 11)